Register of the Walter Campbell Short papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Walter Campbell Short papers
1863-1991
1938-1946
75012
Hoover Institution Archives
6 manuscript boxes, 14 oversize boxes, 3 motion picture film reels (17.9 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, defense statements, photographs, film, scrapbooks, certificates, clippings, congressional prints, and other printed matter relating to Lieutenant General Walter Campbell Short, especially his military career and investigations of defense preparations at the time of the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor. Lt. Gen. Short was in command of the Hawaiian Department of the United States Army at the time of the attack on Pearl Harbor and subsequently held responsible for the defeat, along with Admiral Husband E. Kimmel.
Short, Walter Campbell, 1880-1949.
United States Commission to investigate and report the facts relating to the attack made by Japanese armed forces upon Pearl Harbor in the territory of Hawaii on December 7, 1941.
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1975 with increments received in 1985 and 1991.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Walter Campbell Short was born on March 30, 1880, in Fillmore, Illinois. He graduated from the University of Illinois in 1901 and briefly taught mathematics at Western Military Academy before he was commissioned into the United States Army in 1902. Short was stationed in France during World War I and served as a member of the 1st Division’s general staff and then as Assistant Chief of Staff for the 3rd Army.
Prior to World War II, Short experienced a fairly successful career as a training and staff officer and earned the rank of major general. He served in a variety of locations, such as the Presidio of San Francisco, Alaska, New York, the Philippines, Mexico, Germany, and Puerto Rico. In 1914, Short married Isabel Dean (1893-1984), daughter of Walter C. Dean, who was mayor of Oklahoma City, Oklahoma from 1927 to 1931.
On February 8, 1941, Walter Campbell Short was appointed to Commander of the Hawaiian Department of the United States Army and granted the temporary rank of lieutenant general. Following the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor on December 7, 1941, Short was relieved of his command and reduced to the rank of major general. The Roberts Commission was formed at this time, appointed by President Franklin D. Roosevelt, to investigate and report on the facts of the events leading to the attack. The commission issued their findings in late January of 1942, which stated that both Lt. Gen. Short and Admiral Husband E. Kimmel, Commander-in-Chief of the U.S. Pacific Fleet, were unprepared for the attack and charged them with dereliction of duty. Short officially retired from the military in February 1942 and took a position with Ford Motor Company in Dallas, Texas.
At the conclusion of World War II, a new investigation was launched by Congress to investigate the events surrounding the attack on Pearl Harbor. This new investigation was headed by ten members of Congress known as the Joint Committee on the Investigation of the Pearl Harbor Attack, or the Pearl Harbor Committee. During the investigation proceedings, Short was allowed to give testimony regarding his actions during the Pearl Harbor attack for the first time. He admitted to personal errors of judgement, but argued that Washington had not given him enough warning that an attack was imminent nor had he been supplied with adequate resources for an air defense. Despite testimony from both Lt. Gen. Short and Adm. Kimmel during the proceedings, the committee ultimately concluded that both men were responsible for the defeat.
Lt. Gen. Short died of a chronic heart condition on March 9, 1949, three years after retiring from Ford. Fifty years after his death, on May 25, 1999, the United States Senate passed a non-binding resolution that exonerated Short and Kimmel from the charge of dereliction of duty. This resolution also included a statement urging the president to restore both men to their full war-time ranks; however, the recommendation was never carried out.
Scope and Content of Collection
Writings, correspondence, defense statements, photographs, films, scrapbooks, certificates, clippings, congressional prints, and other printed matter relating to Lieutenant General Walter Campbell Short, especially his military career and investigations of defense preparations at the time of the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor.
United States. Army--Officers.; Pearl Harbor (Hawaii), Attack on, 1941.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.; Motion pictures.
- Biographical File, 1901-1990
  Scope and Contents Note
  Consists of certificates, memorabilia, and other material. Arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Business and place cards, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Certificates, 1901-1990
    - 1901-1941 (Box-folder 1: 2, Box 18)
      Includes Short's diploma from the University of Illinois, his certificate from the Ordre National de la Légion d'honneur, and his army appointment certificates.
    - Army Co-operative Fire Association benefit certificates, 1914-1938 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - Pearl Harbor Commemorative Committee, Inc. resolution honoring Lt. General Walter C. Short (photocopy), 1990 December 7 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Identification card, American Expeditionary Forces, undated (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Military record, undated (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Miscellany, undated (Box-folder 1: 7)
    Includes poem entitled "A Message to Congress" and a list of goods consigned to Lt. Gen. Short.
- Correspondence, 1919-1949
  Includes letters of support regarding the Pearl Harbor investigations, thank yous to those who wrote to the president on Short's behalf, and autograph requests. Also included is correspondence between Lt. Gen. Short and his wife, Isabel Dean Short, and his son, Walter Dean Short. Following the general file, files are arranged alphabetically by correspondent or original file name.
  - General, 1941-1949, undated; bulk 1942
    - 1941, undated (Box-folder 1: 8)
    - 1942 (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - 1944-1945 (Box-folder 1: 10)
    - 1946, 1949 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - American Expeditionary Forces, 1919 June 22 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - "Congratulatory Letters and Telegrams on Promotion to Major General,", 1940 (Box-folder 1: 13-14)
    This correspondence was originally bound in one volume. Includes index.
  - Kimmel, Husband E., 1941 December 8 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - "Personal Correspondence File: Major General Walter C. Short,", 1940 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Short, Isabel Dean, 1914, 1940, and undated (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Short, Walter Dean, 1940-1947 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    Includes a letter to Walter Dean Short regarding the outcome of the initial Pearl Harbor investigation dated 1942.
  - War Department, 1942, 1944, and undated (Box-folder 2: 5)
- Speeches and Writings, 1932-1941, undated
  - "Tar Brush," manuscript, 1932, undated (Box-folder 2: 6-7)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes a version by Isabel dean Short.
  - 6 April 1941, Speech to Chamber of Commerce on Army Day, circa 1941 (Box-folder 2: 8)
    Note
    A copy of this speech appears in Exhibit 1-O of "Statement by Major General Walter C. Short of Events and Conditions Leading up to the Japanese Attack, December 7, 1941" in Pearl Harbor Investigations File.
- Pearl Harbor Investigations File, 1941-1946
  Contains statements, congressional publications, correspondence, maps, and other material related to the Roberts Commission investigation (1941-1942) and the congressional investigation (1945-1946) of the attack on Pearl Harbor. Includes Lt. Gen. Short's official statement, with exhibits, to the Joint Committee on the Investigation of the Pearl Harbor Attack made in 1946.
  - Investigation statements, 1946, undated
    - "Statement by Major General Walter C. Short of Events and Conditions Leading up to the Japanese Attack, December 7, 1941,", undated (Box-folder 2: 9-11)
      Includes statement with exhibits A - 1-R; however, some exhibit documents appear out of order. A digital version of this statement can be found at https://archive.org/details/pearlharborattac30unit
    - "Statement by Major General Walter C. Short, U. S. Army, Retired. Before the Joint Congressional Committee on the Investigation of the Pearl Harbor Attack," prerelease, 1946 January (Box-folder 2: 12)
    - "Statement Reference Secret Documents Pertaining to Pearl Harbor and Not Known to Me Until the Summer of 1944" [sic], typescript, undated (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Congressional prints, 1942, 1945
    - Attack Upon Pearl Harbor by Japanese Armed Forces, report by the United States Commission to Investigate and Report the Facts Relating to the Attack Made by Japanese Armed Forces upon Pearl Harbor in the Territory of Hawaii on December 7, 1941, 1942 (Box-folder 2: 14)
    - Pearl Harbor: Intercepted Diplomatic Messages Sent by the Japanese Government between July 1 and December 8, 1941, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1945
    - Green, Thomas H., 1945 April 12 (Box-folder 2: 16)
    - Hawaiian Department, 1941 December 20 (Box-folder 2: 17)
    - Unidentified, 1942 April 23 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - Governmental Research, Inc. statement, 1945 September 5 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Joint Committee on the Investigation of the Pearl Harbor Attack digest of exhibits, circa 1946 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Maps and summaries of naval positions on December 7, 1941, undated (Oversize 19: 8)
  - Proposed Pearl Harbor investigation resolution, draft, 1946 December (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Travel documents, 1942 January 8-11 (Box-folder 2: 22)
- Isabel Dean Short File, 1892-1957
  Consists of correspondence, sheet music, copyright certificates, and other material related to Isabel Dean Short (1893-1984), wife of Lt. Gen. Short. Her father, Walter C. Dean, was mayor of Oklahoma City from 1927-1931. Arranged alphabetically, followed by miscellany.
  - Correspondence, 1919-1957, undated
    - General, 1919-1944, undated (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Regarding Walter C. Short, 1942-1954, undated; bulk 1949 (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - Crown Music, 1953 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - Kimmel, Husband E., 1957 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - Short, Walter Dean, 1939-1944 (Box-folder 3: 5-6)
  - "The General's Lady," manuscript, 1955 (Box-folder 3: 7-9)
    Includes correspondence regarding the publication of the manuscript.
  - Musical compositions, 1939, 1951, undated
    Includes manuscripts and printed copies of musical scores composed by Isabel Dean Short.
    - Manuscripts, 1939, undated (Box-folder 3: 10-12, 4: 1, 19: 9)
    - Copyright certificates, 1951 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - Photostat negatives, undated (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Walter C. Dean file, 1892-1952, undated (Box-folder 4: 4-5)
    Includes various materials related to Walter C. Dean, including an artist's sketch, news clippings, and his wedding book (contains hair clippings).
  - Miscellany, 1918-1950, undated (Box-folder 4: 6, 19: 1)
    Includes U.S. Army Hawaiian Department identification card, Puerto Rican operator's license, photograph and text used for a press release when Walter Dean Short received the Silver Star Medal, and other material.
- Walter Dean Short File, 1920-1990
  Contains material related to Lt. Gen. Short's son, Walter Dean Short. Includes a membership card, his baby book, correspondence, and military school records. Arranged alphabetically, followed by miscellany.
  - Army Navy Country Club membership card, 1932 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Baby book, 1920-1921 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1990, undated (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - West Point records, 1942 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Miscellany, 1945, undated (Box-folder 4: 11)
    Includes childhood notebook used to practice handwriting and photostat negatives of general order for award of Silver Star Medal.
- Photographs, 1893-1950s
  Includes photographs of Lt. Gen. Short as well as his immediate and extended family. Also included are photographs documenting his military career. Arranged alphabetically by subject followed by miscellany, unidentified persons, and negatives.
  - Family, 1893-1950s, undated (Box-folder 4: 12-16, 5: 1-3, 19: 2-5)
    Includes photographs of Lt. Gen. Short, his wife Isabel, son Walter Dean, and their extended family. Contains tin types.
  - "Honolulu Club and House,", circa 1941 (Box-folder 5: 4)
    Includes photographs of the Shorts' arrival in Hawaii as well as their Honolulu home.
  - "Leavenworth,", undated (Box-folder 5: 5)
    Contains photographs taken at Fort Leavenworth, Kansas.
  - Military, 1917-1941, undated (Box-folder 5: 6)
    Includes photograph of Lt. Gen. Short receiving the Distinguished Service Medal with letter attached dated May 2, 1919.
  - Portraits, undated (Box-folder 5: 7, 19: 6-7)
  - Miscellany, 1916-1944, undated (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - Unidentified persons, undated (Box-folder 6: 1, Box 18)
  - Negatives, undated (Box-folder 6: 2)
- Motion Picture Films, 1940-1941 (Film shelf)
  Three 16mm film reels depicting Lt. Gen. Short's promotion to major general and an examination of troops before the attack on Pearl Harbor.
- Oversize Material, 1901-1955
  Contains photo albums, scrapbooks, and a Confederate States of America war bond. Arranged alphabetically by type and then chronologically.
  - Album, circa 1910s (Box 7)
    Contains photographs of Isabel and Lt. Gen. Short during his early military career at an unidentified military camp. Album has been removed from its bindings due to deterioration.
  - Album, 1918-1947; bulk 1944 (Box 11)
    Contains wedding and family photos of Walter Dean and Emily Short as well as clippings, correspondence, and Walter Dean Short's West Point graduation invitation.
  - Album, 1920s-1944; bulk 1920-1929 (Box 8)
    Contains a clipping announcing Walter Dean Short's marriage to Emily Short, as well as photographs of him as a baby and correspondence.
  - Album, 1934 (Box 9)
    Contains captioned photographs of the 6th U.S. Infantry at various locations in Illinois, Michigan, and Missouri. Also contains three news clippings.
  - Album, 1935 (Box 16)
    Contains photographs taken during the 1935 National Rifle Matches held at Camp Perry, Ohio. Includes photographs of Lt. Gen. Short awarding trophies to the winners of the matches.
  - Album, 1941 (Box 12)
    Contains images of the Shorts' arrival at Fort Shafter in Honolulu, Hawaii taken by the U.S. Army Signal Corps. Also contains clippings and several images of the interior of the Shorts' Honolulu residence.
  - Confederate States of America war bond, 1863 (Box-folder 19: 10)
  - Scrapbook, 1901-1939 (Box 10)
    Contains clippings, photographs, and other printed matter related to Lt. Gen. Short's early military career, including letters regarding his appointment to army lieutenant dated 1901. Also includes several clippings regarding Walter C. Dean's mayoral re-election. Scrapbook has been removed from its original binding due to preservation concerns.
  - Scrapbook, 1922-1940 (Box 13)
    Contains invitations from the White House and for various events. Also includes ticket stubs from the 1939 World's Fair in New York and news clippings. Scrapbook unbound due to preservation concerns.
  - Scrapbook, 1923-1945 (Box 14)
    Contains articles on Walter Dean Short receiving the Bronze Star Medal, his cadet records, and clippings about the end of World War II. Also includes programs from several of Isabel Short's musical performances, photographs, and a first prize ribbon from the 1930 Fort Leavenworth Dog Show.
  - Scrapbook, 1938-1941 (Box 17)
    Contains clippings related to Lt. Gen. Short's military achievements, including his promotion to major general in March of 1940 and to commander of the Hawaiian Department in 1941. Includes some photographs.
  - Scrapbook, 1940-1955 (Box 15)
    Contains clippings regarding Lt. Gen. Short's promotion to commander of the Hawaiian Department, the attack on Pearl Harbor and subsequent investigations, and his death. Includes some correspondence.
- Memorabilia, 1922, undated (Box 20)
  - Gavel of Walter C. Dean, 1922
  - Gold military sash, undated
- Printed Matter, 1920-1956
  Contains clippings, pamphlets, programs, and other printed matter relating to the Short family's activities and the attack on Pearl Harbor. Arranged alphabetically, followed by miscellany.
  - Clippings, 1920-1956
    - "1st Army Maneuvers,", 1939-1940 (Box-folder 6: 3)
      Material removed from its original metal fasteners due to preservation concerns.
    - Articles regarding Walter C. Short, 1929-1955, undated (Box-folder 6: 4)
    - El Imparcial: El Diario Ilustrado de Puerto Rico, 1938 (Box-folder 6: 5)
      Consists of Spanish language articles related to Lt. Gen. Short's military service in Puerto Rico. Material has been removed from its original metal fasteners due to preservation concerns.
    - El Mundo: Diario de la Mañana, 1938 (Box-folder 6: 6)
    - Miscellany, 1920-1956 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - The Final Secrets of Pearl Harbor, pamphlet, 1945 (Box-folder 6: 8)
  - Peace and War: United States Foreign Policy 1931-1941, 1943 (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - The Pointer, Volume XVII, Number 15, 1940 March 22 (Box-folder 6: 10)
  - Programs, 1930-1941, undated (Box-folder 6: 11)
  - The Truth About Pearl Harbor, pamphlet, 1944 (Box-folder 6: 12)
  - U.S. News & World Report, 1954 (Box-folder 6: 13)
    Includes three issues of U.S. World & News Report from April 2, April 16, and December 3, 1954 that feature articles about Pearl Harbor. Articles of note include: "The Big Secret of Pearl Harbor" (April 2), "More About Pearl Harbor" (April 16), and "The Muddle Before Pearl Harbor--Inside Story by Capt. T. B. Kittredge" (December 3).
  - Miscellany, undated (Box-folder 6: 14)
    Includes postcard booklets from Madrid and the Museu Nacional dos Coches in Portugal as well as a reproduction of a York Minster Cathedral etching with text.